<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>David his oath of allegeance to Ierusalem The sermon preached on Act Sunday last in the morning, in St. Maries in Oxford. By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850423</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15625</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15625)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1331:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>David his oath of allegeance to Ierusalem The sermon preached on Act Sunday last in the morning, in St. Maries in Oxford. By Daniel Price Doctor in Divinity.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Davids oath of allegiance to Ierusalem.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15625:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15625:1"/>
            <p>DAVID HIS OATH OF ALLEGEANCE TO IERVSALEM.</p>
            <p>THE SERMON PREACHED ON ACT SVNDAY LAST IN THE MORNING, <hi>IN St</hi>. <hi>MARIES IN OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY DANIEL PRICE <hi>Doctor in Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 137.6.</hi>
               </bibl> Let my tongue cleaue to the roofe of my mouth, if I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre not Ieruſalem aboue my chiefe ioie.</q>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Joseph Barnes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15625:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15625:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIE PRINCE, PRINCE CHARLES DVKE OF <hi>CORNWAILE</hi> AND <hi>YORKE,</hi> THE GREAT BLESSING OF <hi>GREAT BRITTAINE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Lluſtrious <hi>Prince,</hi> your Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>favour</hi> and Princely <hi>bountie,</hi> ſhining this Act vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two of vs, the late <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> of your bleſſed <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> hath giuen <hi>life</hi> and <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to this which I preſume to <hi>preſent</hi> vnto you. It is a <hi>Princes vow,</hi> made to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the <hi>virgin</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>beautie</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> it is <hi>harty</hi> for the <hi>manner, holy</hi> for the <hi>matter,</hi> fit for <hi>theſe times,</hi> wherin becauſe in <hi>Ieruſalem, (Church and Court)</hi> ſome doe vow to <hi>Babylon, Court</hi> &amp; <hi>Country</hi> may obſerue what our <hi>Prophet</hi> ſitting by the waters of <hi>Babylon,</hi> did vow to <hi>Ieruſalem, Religion</hi> is our <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> be you her <hi>Prince,</hi> wee
<pb facs="tcp:15625:3"/>haue ſate lately, and lamentably at the waters of <hi>Babel,</hi> mourning and <hi>mourning,</hi> and would not bee comforted, becauſe HEE was not, who <hi>was</hi> as truely Gods <hi>ſervant,</hi> as his <hi>ſervants</hi> earthly God.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Highneſſe</hi> is now the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> the <hi>daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> the <hi>morning,</hi> the <hi>day</hi> ſtarre, the <hi>ſunſhine,</hi> &amp; <hi>light</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>newly</hi> cleered <hi>firmament,</hi> O then <hi>grace</hi> her, who will <hi>bring</hi> you to further <hi>glory RELIGION.</hi> Bee her <hi>Patrone,</hi> that ſhee <hi>weep</hi> not, bee her <hi>Champion</hi> that ſhee <hi>bleed not.</hi> Let no Popiſh <hi>Philiſtin</hi> come neere the <hi>chaire,</hi> much leſſe, the <hi>eare</hi> of your greatneſſe, to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace truth,</hi> or <hi>wrong faith,</hi> and at all times pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in your ſong. So ſhall all eyes, hearts, hopes, be fixed vpon you here, and all glory, ioy, &amp; happineſſe be <hi>faſtned</hi> vpon you <hi>hence.</hi> For which <hi>purpoſe</hi> ever ſhall bee offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the <hi>humble devotions of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe ſervant, <hi>DANIEL PRICE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Exeter Coll.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 27.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15625:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 137.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>If I forget thee O Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lamentations of <hi>David</hi> were as <hi>dolefull</hi> as <hi>plentifull</hi> for <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abſolon,</hi> for his <hi>friend</hi> and for his <hi>ſonne;</hi> yet more for his friende then for his ſonne, becauſe <hi>Abſolon</hi> his ſonne was his foe, but <hi>Ionathan</hi> his foes ſonne, was his friend. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for <hi>friend</hi> or <hi>ſonne,</hi> is he ſo paſſionate, as for Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem: all the <hi>floudgates</hi> &amp; <hi>cataracts</hi> of affections empt themſelues vpon this ſubiect. His <hi>paſſions</hi> thoſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall acts and operations of the ſoule, linked in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable league of <hi>loue,</hi> with the <hi>ioy</hi> of the earth <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> vrged him ſo farre, that foreſeeing the <hi>ſtorme,</hi> though he lived in a <hi>ſunneſhine, affection</hi> enflamed his <hi>heart,</hi> and his <hi>heart</hi> reſolved into inceſſant teares: he ſmarteth though <hi>vntouched,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyr. Carth Ahu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, almoſt all the Fathers that interpret the Pſalmes iudge this to be Davids.</note> and being vnhurt <hi>lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth,</hi> not his owne <hi>caſe,</hi> but Ieruſalem <hi>Calamity.</hi> And in three Pſalmes, as <hi>Lyra</hi> and <hi>Carth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſian</hi> teach, he deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, the threefold ſacking &amp; ranſacking of <hi>Ieruſalem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which was to be performed by thoſe <hi>Nymrods</hi> of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15625:4"/>earth, that which he foreſaw laſt he lamenteth firſt: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by the <hi>Romans,</hi> whervpon his 74. Pſal. <hi>O God why art thou abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs ſo long, O think vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, thinke vpon the tribe of thine inheritance; deliver not the ſoule of thy turtle doue to the multitude of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:</hi> as alſo that former deſolation by that <hi>plague</hi> of men &amp; <hi>Scourge</hi> of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Antiochus</hi> which occaſioned the 79. Pſalme, <hi>O God the heathen are come into thy poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thy holy temple haue they defiled &amp; made Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a heape of ſtones:</hi> and before either of thoſe the captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Babylon by <hi>Nabuchadonoſor,</hi> that thiſtle which burned vp the Cedars of <hi>Libanus,</hi> which occaſioned this ſorrowfull <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the <hi>embleme</hi> of their <hi>ſighes</hi> and <hi>ſumme</hi> of the <hi>ſorrow</hi> of that deſolation. The firſt mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle done in the old Teſtament is in the 1. of <hi>Geneſis</hi> the 2.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Spiritus Domini ferebatur ſuper aquas.</hi> The firſt mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in the new Teſtament is the ſame, <hi>Spiritus Domini ferebatur ſuper aquas,</hi> The ſpirit of God moved on the waters <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. when our <hi>Saviour</hi> turned the water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>wine:</hi> I ſay not that there is a miracle here, but ſure I am, <hi>Spiritus Domini ferebatur ſuper aquas,</hi> the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> by the ſpirit of <hi>Prophecie,</hi> was with the <hi>Prophet</hi> when he ſate by theſe <hi>waters of Babylon,</hi> deſcribing &amp; deploring <hi>Edoms</hi> cruelty, <hi>Iſraels</hi> miſery. <hi>Ezechiel</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his prophecie by the river of <hi>Cobar, Daniel</hi> by the river <hi>Tigris, Iohn Baptiſt</hi> by the river <hi>Iordane:</hi> but by the waters of <hi>Babylon</hi> rivers of confuſion and deſolation our <hi>Prophet</hi> ſeateth himſelfe, and theſe rivers be rather of <hi>oile</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>water,</hi> they increaſe the flame of his affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; rather <hi>nouriſh</hi> then <hi>diminiſh</hi> his griefe: his eies are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15625:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>as thoſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> like the eies of <hi>Doues</hi> on the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of waters, his eies like the eies of <hi>Doues,</hi> and his voice like the voice of a <hi>Doue, Turtur no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> canit ſed gemit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidor:</hi> the <hi>Doue</hi> was ſent out by <hi>Noah</hi> &amp; was a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of <hi>Comfort</hi> in returning in thoſe waters, the <hi>Doue</hi> came down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our <hi>Saviour</hi> &amp; was a meſſenger of <hi>ioy</hi> in deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding into thoſe waters, but the waters of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lon</hi> haue no <hi>Doue</hi> neere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but <hi>David,</hi> and my text is the voice of that <hi>Turtle</hi> heard in that la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, <hi>If I forget thee O Ieruſalem, then let my right hande forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Votum eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin, certé votivum quiddam eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calv. in Pſ. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> they be <hi>words,</hi> or if you will <hi>vowes,</hi> or rather more then <hi>words</hi> or <hi>vowes:</hi> they receiue fire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the altar of his heart, and the <hi>fire</hi> of his <hi>loue</hi> liues yet in them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither the <hi>diſtance</hi> of the <hi>place,</hi> nor <hi>continuance</hi> of the <hi>time,</hi> ſince they were vttered, can quench them but that their <hi>ſound</hi> is gone out into all nations, the ſighes of the Prophets ſoule, and the billowes of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons</hi> water yeeld no other wofull warbling <hi>murmur</hi> but the <hi>Eccho</hi> of this Text, <hi>If I forget thee O Ieruſalem, then let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If I forget</hi>] <hi>Memory</hi> is more <hi>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>moone,</hi> it is a <hi>glaſſe</hi> placed behinde in the head, mans fall brake this glaſſe: ſince, it is crazed, daſhed, dazeled, of all the faculties ſooneſt decaieth: at the beſt, it is but <hi>ſorrowes ſtore houſe</hi> &amp; <hi>ſins table booke,</hi> it recordeth our woes &amp; repreſenteth our wants, it is a <hi>roome</hi> hung with the maps of all themiſeries we endured. But our Prophet by a devoted confirmed ſanctified memory doth poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe himſelfe with the repreſentation of the <hi>place of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15625:5"/>Religion.</hi> The motions and <hi>reſolutions</hi> of all the the <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall ſpheres</hi> cannot diſturbe much leſſe deſtroy his <hi>meditations</hi> vpon <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> This as a ſwift winged <hi>Seraphin,</hi> is fled vp to heaven, and there recorded, <hi>If I forget thee O Ieruſalem, the ioy of the earth, Queene of the nations, City of God, beauty of the whole world, thee O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> ſeate or the <hi>Temple,</hi> Princeſſe of the <hi>Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> chaire of the <hi>Monarch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> throne of the <hi>kingdome,</hi> Golden head of the <hi>picture.</hi> No, <hi>Iſrael</hi> may forget <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> forget <hi>Iſrael</hi> their <hi>father,</hi> the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> may forget her <hi>childe,</hi> and the childe exenterate his owne <hi>mother,</hi> but <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the apple of Gods eie, the ſignet on his finger, the Virgin of the Eaſt, beautie of the earth, his <hi>faire one, deere one, little one, onely</hi> one, ſhalbe had in everlaſting <hi>remembrance. If I forget thee O Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi> The beſt exterior member of the <hi>body,</hi> the <hi>hand,</hi> the beſt vſe of the hand <hi>cunning:</hi> but let hand and <hi>cunning</hi> periſh, the right &amp; beſt vſe of the right hand <hi>periſh,</hi> let neither his <hi>tongue</hi> ſtirre, nor his <hi>hand</hi> touch his <hi>harp,</hi> nay let his <hi>eies</hi> fall into the <hi>holes</hi> of his <hi>head,</hi> and all his <hi>faculties</hi> faile, <hi>rather</hi> then he <hi>faile</hi> to remember <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which few words ſhew the much <hi>loue</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to the place of Gods <hi>ſervice:</hi> and as <hi>Reverend Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the words noteth,<note place="margin">Calvin in <hi>137.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Teſtantur Dei cultores adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitâ imprecatione memoriam ſanctae vrbis cordibus ſuis, ſemper fore infixam,, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vnquam deletam iri quicquid acciderit:</hi> the true worſhippers of God doe ſeale with an <hi>imprecation</hi> the remembrance and reverend regard of <hi>Religion,</hi> never to be rooted from their ſoules, to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15625:5"/>their ſong <hi>day</hi> and <hi>night,</hi> their <hi>morning</hi> and <hi>evening</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their <hi>meate</hi> and <hi>drinke,</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light of their <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>breath</hi> of their noſtrils, never to be ſeparated, never to be divorced from them; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man ſaying, as our Prophet, <hi>If I forget thee O Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, then let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diviſio Textus. </seg>
               </label> I haue <hi>numbred</hi> the words, let vs goe to the ſikle of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> and there waigh them. 1. The <hi>ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>exaggeration</hi> of his vow: <hi>If I forget thee.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the <hi>place,</hi> or <hi>ſubiect,</hi> or <hi>obiect</hi> occaſioning his vow: <hi>Thee O Ieruſalem.</hi> Thirdly, the <hi>obligation,</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation,</hi> or if you pleaſe, <hi>his oath of allegiance to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem: then let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi> All of them be as the ingredients for the holy incenſe, ſweet ſmelling ſavours vnto God: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the <hi>firſt</hi> a <hi>fervent</hi> and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement vow, <hi>holy</hi> for the matter, <hi>harty</hi> for the maner. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>ſecond</hi> the moſt holy place of the moſt high, the <hi>Parallel</hi> of loſt <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and <hi>figure</hi> of the hope for <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> a reſemblance of every <hi>faithfull</hi> mans ſoule, &amp; the repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the militant &amp; triumphant Church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third a powerfull and faithfull confirmation of the Prophets profeſſion and patheticall reſolution, <hi>let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Ho: Reverend,</hi> all beloued, lend your eares to that ſubiect, to which <hi>David</hi> the <hi>type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſonne of <hi>David</hi> lent their teares. <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> hath friends every where, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> wants <hi>Religion,</hi> I meane expecteth that you wil ſtand to her, otherwiſe, <hi>vt quid ſtatis hic otioſi,</hi> why ſtand you here <hi>idle?</hi> but <hi>per ſilentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſenſum video, Acuanus</hi> ſpake in the ſame kind,<note place="margin">Acuanus in Pſal.</note> I ſee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15625:6"/>your conſent by your ſilence, and hope your <hi>faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> will never entertaine <hi>forgetfulneſſe,</hi> eſpecially of <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> which profeſſion, was <hi>Davids</hi> practiſe and my firſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forgetfulneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Part. <hi>Bon. in Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> by the <hi>ſchooles</hi> is defined to be <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae lubricatio,</hi> and ſo <hi>Bonaventure</hi> ſpeakes on the 119. Pſalme, it is a ſlippery <hi>inconſtancy</hi> of the memory whereby the beſt part of the <hi>minde,</hi> the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> can neither fitly <hi>receaue,</hi> nor faithfully <hi>retaine</hi> thoſe <hi>ſpecies</hi> which are repreſented to it. It is like to that ſwift <hi>Kiſhon</hi> which ſwept Siſera's ſouldiers away, it is a precipitate <hi>torrent,</hi> the <hi>obliterating,</hi> and <hi>expunging</hi> of knowledge, the very <hi>index expurgatorius</hi> of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the cloud of the <hi>minde,</hi> and ecclypſe of the <hi>memorie.</hi> The fathers diſtinguiſh it into two parts: firſt a vſefull and <hi>laudable:</hi> ſecond an hatefull and <hi>damnable</hi> forgetfulneſſe.<note place="margin">Bernard in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerueth that the name <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> ſignifieth <hi>forgetfulneſſe,</hi> and as the tribe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> dwelt part on the one ſide, part on the other ſide <hi>Iordan, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>totus Manaſſes Iordanem non tranſiit,</hi> ſo there is a <hi>forgetfulneſſe</hi> which ſtayeth from paſſing <hi>Iordan,</hi> &amp; another <hi>forgetfulnes</hi> which leadeth through <hi>Iordan,</hi> to the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jt is a wonder that <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſhould bee the father of a Tribe: an <hi>Egyptian</hi> bare him, <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court was the place of his breeding, neither <hi>Nurſe</hi> nor <hi>Mother</hi> could giue <hi>benedictionem patriae:</hi> when he came for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> bleſſing <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the father led him by the left hand, and <hi>Iacob</hi> the grand-father laid his left hand vpon him, neither father, nor grand-father gaue him <hi>benedictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15625:6"/>dextrae,</hi> the bleſſing of the right hand. When hee came to tearme of <hi>inheritance,</hi> the tribe was divided, <hi>Iordan</hi> divided them, halfe on the one ſide,<note place="margin">Spedi geneal. ante Biblia.</note> the other on the other, no tribe ſo devided as <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> neither had <hi>benedictionem terrae. Manaſſes</hi> was but nephew to the <hi>Tribes,</hi> &amp; loſt his birth-right as <hi>Eſau</hi> did. <hi>Gedeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> was of this <hi>tribe,</hi> whoſe ſonnes were all <hi>ſlaine, Zelophehad</hi> of this <hi>tribe,</hi> who had no <hi>ſonnes</hi> but <hi>daughters.</hi> Many monuments of <hi>orbitancy,</hi> of <hi>defection,</hi> and <hi>oblivion</hi> in this <hi>tribe;</hi> and yet many Princes, many Prophets, were of it.</p>
            <p>I follow S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> his alluſion, that <hi>Manaſſes</hi> the eldeſt ſonne of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſhould bee <hi>forgetfulneſse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> It is much, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was now a <hi>Prince</hi> in Egypt, who had bin a <hi>priſoner</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Ioſeph</hi> whoſe feete they hurt in the <hi>ſtockes,</hi> that the yron entred into his ſoule, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from the ſtate of a <hi>Priſoner</hi> to be a <hi>Prince,</hi> his firſt fruit to be <hi>forgetfulnes,</hi> it is very much. <hi>Adams</hi> firſt fruit <hi>Cain</hi> to be a <hi>murderer, Iacobs</hi> firſt fruit <hi>Reuben,</hi> to be <hi>incestuous; Aarons</hi> firſt fruit <hi>Nadab,</hi> to be <hi>contumacious; Davids</hi> firſt fruit <hi>Ammon,</hi> to bee <hi>adulterous; Salomons</hi> firſt fruit <hi>Rhehoboam,</hi> to be <hi>Idolatrous;</hi> ſheweth, that theſe holy men did not offer their firſts fruits, their eldeſt <hi>ſonnes</hi> vnto God: but <hi>Ioſeph</hi> almoſt the leſt and <hi>youngeſt</hi> of his brethren, ſaued from the <hi>pit,</hi> ſaued from the <hi>priſon,</hi> now a <hi>Prince</hi> in Egypt, and <hi>Manaſſes, forgetfulneſſe,</hi> his firſt ſonne, enforceth that all that are dignified &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, are moſt ready to forget the ſtate, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence <hi>God</hi> hath brought them. They are the ſons of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> not of <hi>Iacob;</hi> he wanne by yeelding, and was honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15625:7"/>by his halting, by his humbling ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> the lower he ſtoups to the earth, the neerer, the better his advantage for this bleſſing,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom.</note> 
               <hi>felices hi ex tribu Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſsis qui humilitatem induunt, authoritatem exuunt, Leo</hi> giueth the reaſon, <hi>Humilitas animi ſublimitas Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtiani,</hi> happy is their forgetfulnes, the ſtarres of whoſe firmament, being great, yet ſeeme leſſe then the earth, this <hi>fargetfulneſſe</hi> is <hi>virtus honorata,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> an humble mind in an honorable place,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> it is a <hi>lowly valley</hi> ſweetly planted, and <hi>pleaſantly</hi> watered, a royall <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſy</hi> with a low faile, a holy <hi>temple</hi> with a low roofe. He is a true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> more then a <hi>Nathiniel,</hi> he is of the band of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> or rather the <hi>Centurion</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Iacob. Manaſſes. David. Eſdr. Centurion. Paul. Iohn Bap.</note> who in the Goſpell cryeth <hi>Domine non ſum dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> which is the voice of 4 in the old <hi>Teſtament,</hi> and 3 in the new, happy ſonnes of the tribe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> bleſſed practiſes of forgetfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond legion of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> paſſing over <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> J place thoſe, who in a charitable forgetfulneſſe forgiue all wrongs done to them It was <hi>Peter</hi> his que<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtion, Mat. 18. How often ſhall J forgiue my brother? How often in a day, as <hi>Luke</hi> addeth, the anſwer is 70 times 7.<note place="margin">Ierom.</note> that is, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Ierom</hi> 490 times, if there may be ſo many ebbings and flowings in the ſea of thy paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtine</hi> giueth the reaſon,<note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> why ſeaventie times ſeaven, from <hi>Adam</hi> to Chriſt there were ſeaventy ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, and when Chriſt came, hee forgaue all the tranſgreſſions of mankind diffuſed into ſo many <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations:</hi> ſo alſo ſhould a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> remit as many offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as in the compaſſe of his life can bee committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15625:7"/>him. <hi>Tully</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tully. Amb.</note> reſtify that they forgat nothing but iniuries. Happy is he that ſo conquereth himſelfe, as that wrongs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conquer him; he is aboue nature, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeemeth below himſelfe, for not to reſiſt being vrged, is more then Heroicall. <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> giueth him this chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, he is Gods beſt <hi>witneſſe,</hi> Natures beſt <hi>child,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theoph.</note> the ſureſt <hi>friend,</hi> the lateſt <hi>enimie,</hi> the greateſt <hi>conquerour.</hi> So farre <hi>forgetfulneſſe</hi> is vſefull, and the poſteritie of <hi>Manaſses</hi> fruitfull. But the <hi>forgetfulneſſe,</hi> againſt which <hi>David</hi> with an execration voweth, is a <hi>neglect</hi> bred by the corruption of <hi>nature,</hi> nouriſhed by the ecclipſe of <hi>grace,</hi> whereby Gods bleſſings be either not <hi>reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred</hi> or not <hi>regarded.</hi> This is the <hi>ruſt</hi> of the ſenſes, &amp; <hi>Canker</hi> of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> mans worſt <hi>inmate,</hi> ſinnes greateſt <hi>aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate. Accipiendis eſt indignus, qui fuerit acceptis ingratus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eern.</note> man hereby enioyeth not thoſe he formerly <hi>receaved,</hi> not <hi>receaueth</hi> thoſe which futurely he <hi>expecteth:</hi> Our Prophets reſolution is otherwiſe, <hi>If I forget.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cadit oblivte,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, but God will not, cannot forget.<note place="margin">Th 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> putteth it among thoſe <hi>actus Deo inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venientes.</hi> Yet as the iuſt be had in his eternall <hi>remembrance,</hi> ſo the wicked bee <hi>forgotten,</hi> that is, cauſed to be <hi>forgotten,</hi> vtterly oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the earth. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> proue this:<note place="margin">Bern.</note> the <hi>ouenant</hi> made to <hi>David</hi> is, that for ever there ſhould be a <hi>light in Iſrael. Rhehoboam ſinned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhehoboam.</hi> 1 King 11.</note> to tribes were cut of yet the kingdome ſhall not <hi>vtterly be taken way, Erit lux Davidis in Iſrael,</hi> 1. Kings 11.34. <hi>Abijam</hi> his ſon, <hi>ditionum &amp; vitiorum haeres,</hi> as <hi>Lyra</hi> names him, <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15625:8"/>and <hi>augments</hi> his fathers ſinnes, <hi>the axe is laid to the root of the tree,</hi> the Scepter begins to wither, <hi>the Lord is ready to deſtroy him,</hi> yet he remembers his <hi>Covenant, Erit Lux Davidis in Ieruſalem</hi> 1. King 15.4.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abiiam.</hi> 1. King. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Iehoram</hi> ioineth with <hi>Ahab,</hi> whoſe poſteritie woe and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance was to <hi>vndermine;</hi> all <hi>Iehorams</hi> children are <hi>ſlaine,</hi> now the light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to bee <hi>extinguiſhed,</hi> but the Lord remembreth his covenant to <hi>David,</hi> though all the ſeed <hi>royall</hi> of <hi>Iudah</hi> was thought to bee <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> yet <hi>Ioaſh</hi> is ſaued, preſerued from the <hi>horrid</hi> maſſacre, hid in the bed chamber, the <hi>Covenant</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth, <hi>Erit Lux Davidis in Ieruſalem</hi> 2. Chron. 21. It is a ſpeech vſuall in the Kings and Chronicles,<note place="margin">Iehoram. 2. Chr. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Erit lux Davidis in Ieruſalem,</hi> the Lord would continue a light in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo did the Lord vntill he came, who was the light of the Gentiles, and the glory of his people Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, a <hi>continua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> a ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, an emanation of the root of <hi>Ieſſe. Davids</hi> ſeed ſhal remaine among the poſterities, <hi>impij autem non ſic,</hi> it is not ſo with <hi>Ahab,</hi> he &amp; his ſhal be forgotten, <hi>God</hi> hath forgotten him, hee turneth his face from him, and <hi>there is none to helpe him:</hi> a little <hi>vineyard</hi> rooteth, eateth, obliterateth him, and all his. They were al like thoſe that periſhed at <hi>Endor,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the dung of the earth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2. King 21.17.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> is accurſed by <hi>Eliah,</hi> his wife, and children <hi>curſed,</hi> vengeance dogges him to his <hi>end, Ahab</hi> is ſlaine in battell, dogges licke his blood, <hi>Iehoram</hi> his ſonne wounded in battell, after ſlaine by <hi>Iehu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 22.</note> dogges lickt his blood, <hi>Iezebel</hi> his wife caſt downe from the window is ſlaine, <hi>Ahaziah</hi> her ſonne fel from the window,<note place="margin">2. King. 22.</note> is ſlaine. Dogges lickt but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15625:8"/>the blood of <hi>Ahab,</hi> but they eate the body of <hi>Iezebel:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 1.</note> his two ſonnes both <hi>Kings,</hi> caſt out as filthie carcaſes, and yet the <hi>Tragedy</hi> not ended, <hi>vengance</hi> hath another <hi>ſcene,</hi> ſeaventie of his <hi>ſonnes</hi> were ſlaine. <hi>Athaliah</hi> ſought to deſtroy all the blood royall,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 22.</note> and <hi>feminine crueltie exceedeth maſculine,</hi> ſaith the Hiſtorian,<note place="margin">Lamprid.</note> but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaliah</hi> could not deſtroy <hi>Ioas,</hi> one remaines. <hi>Iehu</hi> ſlew two and forty of <hi>Ahaziahs</hi> brethren, and none <hi>remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> but this number is almoſt doubled,<note place="margin">2. King. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſeaventie</hi> ſons all of their blood royall derived from <hi>vena baſilica</hi> of <hi>Ahab</hi> all ſlaine, yet not an end, for an <hi>Epilogue,</hi> as if deſtruction were come to a perpetuall end, and the memoriall of them periſhed with them,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Iehu</hi> ſlew all his great men, all his <hi>Captaines,</hi> all his <hi>kinſfolke,</hi> all his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> all his ſervants, til hee left him not one remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, 2. Kings 10.11. Theſe might ſay,<note place="margin">2. King. 10.11. Pſal. 10.11.</note> as thoſe in the Pſalme Pſ. 10.11. <hi>God hath forgotten them, hee turneth his face from them, and there is none to deliuer them.</hi> But this forgetting is <hi>effectus irae,</hi> not <hi>defectus memoriae,</hi> in God it is a note of his <hi>puniſhing,</hi> not of his not <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring,</hi> it is the <hi>effect</hi> of his <hi>wrath,</hi> not a <hi>defect</hi> of his <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> He ſeeth all, knoweth all, remembreth all, only God may truely ſay, I <hi>will not forget.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moyſes</hi> led the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> many daies iourney out of the way in their paſſage to <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philo.</note> my <hi>iourny</hi> is to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; Pardon</hi> this laſt neceſſary <hi>outroad.</hi> I come nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to our Prophets <hi>meaning</hi> and <hi>remembring:</hi> whoſe <hi>harty reſolution</hi> leads vs to this <hi>holy poſition.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a true Chriſtian alwaies to remember, never to forget the bleſſings, that his God hath beſtowed vpon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15625:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>Natures <hi>impotencie</hi> by ſinnes <hi>obliquity</hi> hath ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrakt all the faculties of the ſoule, the vnderſtanding is <hi>blind,</hi> the will <hi>madde,</hi> the minde <hi>lame,</hi> the memory, as the man betweene <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> &amp; <hi>Iericho,</hi> ſore wounded. <hi>Grace</hi> as the good <hi>Samaritan</hi> cureth and recovereth theſe.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>Nihil facilius putreſcit quàm amor,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> nothing decaieth ſooner the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue, <hi>Putreſcit, ſeneſcit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium,</hi> a benefit ſoone antiquateth and putrifieth. Of all the powers of the ſoule <hi>delicata, tenera, maximè fragilis memoria, in quam primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenectus incurrit:</hi> white haires be not more preſent <hi>harbingers</hi> of old age then the tender, delicate, britle memory, which ſooneſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xeth old: no faculty ſooner then memory, no <hi>apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of memory, ſooner waxeth old then a <hi>benefit.</hi> Men forget thoſe <hi>favours,</hi> the authors wherof be their dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obiects, how eaſie then to forget God they ſee not! When al the world ſitteth as at the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> Grace as the <hi>Angel</hi> deſcendeth and healeth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proclivities to forgetfulnes of thoſe that be Gods children.<note place="margin">Tully.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> compares <hi>Lucullus</hi> and <hi>Hortenſius</hi> to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, both of wonderful memories, but preferreth <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus</hi> before <hi>Hortenſius,</hi> becauſe hee remembred <hi>matters,</hi> the other but <hi>words.</hi> But the excellenteſt <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect</hi> of all others, either for the <hi>memory</hi> to account, or for any part of the ſoule to <hi>conceiue,</hi> is the meditations of the Lords bleſſings. Happy is he that maketh a <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome houſe</hi> in his ſoule in this <hi>kind,</hi> that ſetteth downe all the <hi>bleſſings</hi> of God that came into his <hi>haven,</hi> that remembreth the Lord, as he hath <hi>remembred</hi> him, that nameth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> over ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as God reckoneth the <hi>ſtarres</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15625:9"/>and calleth them al by their <hi>names:</hi> and though he can not in that <hi>number</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> that God hath beſtowed them on him, becauſe they be more then the <hi>haires</hi> of his head, yet with <hi>David</hi> ſummes then vp, <hi>Quidretri buam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> what ſhal I giue to the Lord for al the benefits he hath done vnto me?<note place="margin">Bern. ep.</note> 
               <hi>Renumeratio haec Remuneratio quaedam,</hi> this is continuall incenſe of the ſoule, <hi>gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aſcenſus, gratiae deſcenſus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi> It was <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas indiuiduus comes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ion. 2.</note> when my ſoule fainted I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Lord: when his ſoule was not only diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, but almoſt <hi>overwhelmed,</hi> he crieth out, I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the Lord. The <hi>Diſciples</hi> only on the ſea in the boat, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with <hi>ſaluation</hi> it ſelfe, cry out, <hi>Maſter we periſh,</hi> the <hi>maſt</hi> of their <hi>faith</hi> was ſhaken, the <hi>anker</hi> of their <hi>hope</hi> almoſt broken, <hi>Maſter we periſh!</hi> But <hi>Ionas</hi> not in a <hi>boat on</hi> but <hi>in</hi> the ſea, in the wombe of a <hi>Whale,</hi> in the <hi>bottom</hi> &amp; <hi>belly</hi> of the <hi>ſea, I remembred the Lord,</hi> ſaith he. <hi>David</hi> may forget his owne people and fathers houſe, forget the wife of his <hi>boſome,</hi> and the fruit of his loines, yea forget to eate his owne <hi>bread,</hi> yet his memory never faileth him in this <hi>ſervice,</hi> to reach to the true <hi>obiect,</hi> the faithfull <hi>continuall</hi> meditations of Gods mercies, the <hi>ingeminated eiaculations</hi> of <hi>remembring</hi> &amp; thankſ giving. God hath beene <hi>bountifull</hi> in <hi>mercies, David</hi> will be <hi>plentifull</hi> in theſe holy <hi>meditations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe of which <hi>Doctrine</hi> is to incite &amp; encourage vs to be exerciſed in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual <hi>meditations</hi> of Gods continued <hi>mercies.</hi> It is the faithfulleſt <hi>coniunction</hi> of the ſoule with <hi>God, coeleſtis eſt mercatura,</hi> ſaith <hi>Acuanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acuanus in Pſ.</note> it is a celeſtial trade, betweene God and man, when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15625:10"/>man becommeth remembrancer to God his great be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefactour. O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>bleſſed brethren,</hi> practiſe <hi>Davids</hi> holy, and daily exerciſe herein! Looke vpon the kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bended knees of his ſoule, lifting vp eies, hands,<note place="margin">Pſ. 22.</note> hart to heaven in 22. Pſalme, <hi>Thou O Lord art he that tooke me out of my mothers wombe, thou waſt my hope whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> I <hi>hanged on my mothers breaſts, thou art my God from my mothers wombe.</hi> In this <hi>great</hi> &amp; honorable aſſembly now we are all met, for cauſe of reioicing and comfort wee are hereby <hi>reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred,</hi> what God hath done for vs ſince the time hee made vs, that he hath created vs out of the <hi>ſlime</hi> of the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; put living &amp; <hi>reaſonable</hi> ſouls into vs. It is <hi>Iobs</hi> queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Why died</hi> I <hi>not in the womb, why gaue</hi> I <hi>not vp the ghoſt, when</hi> I <hi>came from the belly, why did not the knees prevent me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 3.</note> 
               <hi>or the breaſts that</hi> I <hi>might not ſucke?</hi> we may aſke in a thankfull <hi>awfull feare,</hi> as he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in a wilfull <hi>wofull fury.</hi> The Lord hath nurſed vs vp in a civill and well manerd <hi>country,</hi> hath redeemed vs with the blood of his <hi>Sonne,</hi> viſited vs with the <hi>light</hi> of his <hi>goſpell,</hi> iuſtified vs with the <hi>power</hi> of his <hi>grace,</hi> &amp; fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our garners with <hi>ſtore,</hi> &amp; our baskets with <hi>increaſe,</hi> and hath raiſed vp many of vs, when wee were lowly in our owne <hi>eies,</hi> and hath prevented <hi>vs with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of good things. Who ſo is wiſe will ponder theſe things, and never forget the loving kindneſſe of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! we are not more vnable, to <hi>helpe</hi> our ſelues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>vnapt</hi> to acknowledge the help of God. Some <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticall Sceptick</hi> may tell me, this is too popular too vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for this <hi>Comitial</hi> aſſembly. But let him looke into <hi>Davids practiſe;</hi> I will praiſe thy name in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15625:10"/>the <hi>great congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> The temple was called the houſe of <hi>thankſgiuing,</hi> the daily ſacrifice was the oblation of <hi>thankſgiving;</hi> once a yeare there was a ſolemne gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall feaſt of <hi>thankſgiving,</hi> and now the great <hi>Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> of the Lordes Supper is <hi>Euchariſtia</hi> the ſacrament of <hi>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kſgiving.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſm.</note> 
               <hi>Sluggiſhnes</hi> was indorſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doores of the <hi>Sybarites,</hi> forgetfulnes is faſtned vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ours, it ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to vs, as the leproſie of <hi>Gehezei.</hi> O that every one would put his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d into his <hi>boſome,</hi> to ſee how leprouſe he is!<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> this <hi>Epidemicall Contagion</hi> is as water in our <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> and like <hi>oile</hi> in our <hi>bones.</hi> There was a time, that I may ſpeake as <hi>Hierome</hi> did, <hi>Debora ſedebat ſub Palma,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier.</note> the Paragon of mortall Princes, <hi>Debora</hi> the woman after Gods own heart, the virgin <hi>Queene</hi> of the earth, the <hi>glory</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> &amp; <hi>envy</hi> of the infidel world, like vnto whom wee never had king or <hi>Queene</hi> before her; ELIZABETH lived, &amp; like a gracious <hi>mother</hi> dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſed vs: moſt of vs were borne in her <hi>golden daies,</hi> all of vs <hi>bleſſed</hi> by <hi>Peace</hi> within her <hi>wals,</hi> and <hi>plenteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> within her <hi>Palaces,</hi> by that noble <hi>Progreſse</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> within all her <hi>kingdome,</hi> all her <hi>time.</hi> But we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got this, and therefore when <hi>Nature</hi> had given her <hi>fulneſse</hi> of <hi>daies, virtue</hi> fulneſſe of <hi>grace, providence</hi> ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>riches, eſtimation</hi> fulneſſe of <hi>honour, Debora</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, and how ſoone was ſhee forgotten! ſhee was gathered to her <hi>fathers,</hi> and as <hi>happy</hi> in her life, ſo <hi>holy</hi> in her death, ſhee went to reſt with the <hi>greateſt</hi> token of divine favour, maugre that horrid fury of <hi>Parſons,</hi> the curſe of his <hi>name,</hi> and <hi>plague</hi> of his nation, who in his laſt <hi>gaſpes,</hi> as if he had learned <hi>Iobes</hi> wiues counſell,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15625:11"/>to <hi>blaſpheme God and die,</hi> brake the impoſtume of his <hi>then</hi> poiſoned, cankred, now (I feare) damned ſoule, &amp; left that <hi>infection</hi> in papers behinde him to <hi>engaſter</hi> the name and memory of that <hi>bleſſed Queene,</hi> in life more then <hi>Saint,</hi> and <hi>now</hi> equall with <hi>Angels.</hi> How ſoone was ſhee forgot! After her <hi>deceaſe</hi> the darkeſt daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a <hi>day,</hi> that ever our <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try ſaw,</hi> al eies <hi>ſtreaming</hi> with <hi>teares,</hi> all <hi>hearts</hi> breaking with <hi>ſighes,</hi> our <hi>firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> ful of <hi>clowds,</hi> the ſun roſe in the <hi>North,</hi> as gl rious as ever before, in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> the entrance of our day ſtar was, <hi>roſeo cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſole,</hi> Infinit bleſſings of vnion &amp; Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by our <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> Infinite deliverances of <hi>David</hi> and his ſeed, the foundation of <hi>poſterity</hi> and <hi>proſperity laid,</hi> all <hi>clowdes</hi> removed. <hi>Salomon</hi> the Prince renowned through the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world, al <hi>beames</hi> of expectation <hi>reflexed</hi> vpon him, the <hi>lines</hi> of the whole <hi>circumference</hi> met in Prince HENRY as in the <hi>Center,</hi> the eies that <hi>ſaw him bleſſed him, the eares that hard him gaue witneſse to him,</hi> all acclamations ſound this, <hi>bleſſed the wombe that bare thee, and the pappes that gaue thee ſucke.</hi> But we <hi>forgot this,</hi> we all admired his perſon, his deportment, his wiſdome, his grace with God &amp; men, but we <hi>forgot</hi> to be thankfull to God, that had given ſuch a <hi>Prince</hi> to men: our <hi>vnthankfulnes ſlew h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> that renowned <hi>plant,</hi> as the firſt <hi>flowre</hi> of the figge tree, in the <hi>prime</hi> &amp; <hi>bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> of his age, was <hi>tranſlated</hi> to <hi>heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Religion</hi> wept, <hi>vertue</hi> bled at his dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h &amp; the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> world was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to <hi>expire,</hi> yet gracious Prince HENRY is forgot, the Jewel of <hi>Nature</hi> modell of <hi>grace,</hi> religions <hi>Champion, humani generis deliciae,</hi> the light and life of <hi>mankind</hi> is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15625:11"/>already forgot: ſo <hi>ſenſeleſſe</hi> and <hi>ſtupid</hi> and <hi>horrid</hi> is our vnthankfulneſſe. If wee had no other <hi>ſinnes</hi> but <hi>forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> and no other <hi>forgetſulneſſe</hi> then of renowned <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> and bleſſed <hi>P. Henry,</hi> this were enough to <hi>ſhake,</hi> nay to <hi>ſink</hi> vs: it is not a <hi>worm</hi> or <hi>moath</hi> vpon vs, but a <hi>viper</hi> hanging on our hand, <hi>an embleme of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> Wherefore to <hi>land</hi> this point, <hi>Ho: Reverend,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed Chriſtians,</hi> ſet vp pillars of <hi>remembrance</hi> in the faculty of your memory, for all the bleſſings God hath ſhewed to you. Be meditating of the Lords <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> from day to day, let body and ſoule bee free from the <hi>plagues,</hi> that fall vpon both, by neglect of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the bleſſings to <hi>both.</hi> But I leaue this, leaſt I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my ſecond part <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and <hi>If I forget thee O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, then let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Many glorious things are ſpoken of thee thou city of God,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was the Elect city of God,<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> holy and moſt glorious,<note place="margin">Villalpand. in Ezekiel.</note> built vpon the holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, this exceeding all other cities, as their Temple all other buildings. It was ſituated in the midſt of the world, and by <hi>rude</hi> and <hi>polite, divine</hi> and <hi>prophane</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſtiled the <hi>center of the earth,</hi> and the midſt of all natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <hi>Strabo</hi> thinks that <hi>Moyſes</hi> built it, but that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture contradictes: but Scripture is plaine that <hi>Iacob</hi> dwelt there, Gen. 33.18. It was built,<note place="margin">Gen. 33.18.</note> as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth two <hi>thouſand</hi> twenty &amp; three yeares after the creation. <hi>Melcheſedech</hi> was the firſt founder and king of it 50 yeares, &amp; called it <hi>Salem,</hi> which as ſome think, is that which is by Homer called <hi>Solyma.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Let, in Pſal.</note> The <hi>Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, Cananites</hi> poſſeſſed it eight hundred twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty foure
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15625:12"/>yeares, then <hi>David</hi> rooted them out, and the city co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in perfect <hi>beautie,</hi> as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> accounteth, foure <hi>hundred</hi> ſeaventie and ſeaven yeares, in compaſſe, ſaith <hi>Strabo,</hi> ſix miles, 2 hundred and fiftie paces. In the olde <hi>Teſtament</hi> it was ſeaven times beſieged by <hi>Shiſhak</hi> K. of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 14. 2. King. 4. 2. King. 18. 2. King. 19. 2 Chr. 33.11. 2. King. 24.</note> 1. King. 14. by <hi>Ioas</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2. King. 4. by <hi>Reſhim</hi> king of <hi>Aram,</hi> 2. King. 18. by <hi>Senacherib</hi> king of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> 2. King. 19. by the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> in the time of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> 2. Chro. 33.11. by <hi>Pharaoh Necho</hi> in the time of <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> 2. Kin. 24. Laſtly in the time of <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> by <hi>Nabuchadonoſor</hi> that <hi>ſcourge</hi> of heaven, which <hi>fatal,</hi> though not <hi>finall,</hi> deſolation was foreſeen in this Pſal. The originall is <hi>Ieruſchalaijm</hi> in the duall number, for there were two cities, <hi>Salem</hi> and <hi>Syon,</hi> both ſiſters, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> dwelt in the one the great and kingly tribe, <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> in the other, the leaſt and youngeſt tribe. It was never perfect til <hi>Solomons</hi> time, for <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was their King, but wanted <hi>ſucceſsion;</hi> then the <hi>Iebuſits</hi> inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and poſſeſſed it, <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> ſets againſt the <hi>Iebuſites,</hi> kills their king, but obtaines not the Caſtel, the fort of <hi>Syon; David</hi> conquereth them, and obtaineth the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell. Yet there was no Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple al this time. A <hi>praefigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Temple there was long before. <hi>Abraham</hi> in the 2 thouſand and twentie yeare of the world built an altar here, on the mount <hi>Moriah,</hi> but ſacrificed not <hi>Iſaac,</hi> for which he <hi>built the</hi> altar. <hi>David</hi> about the two thouſand eight hundred yeare of the world built an <hi>altar,</hi> and ſacrificed on the ſame <hi>mount,</hi> but the altar had no <hi>Temple.</hi> After this <hi>Solomon</hi> built the <hi>Temple,</hi> and the altars in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and offred <hi>20 thouſand Oxen,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15625:12"/>and a <hi>hundred and twentie thouſand ſheep.</hi> Yet the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> was not <hi>perfect,</hi> there lacketh the <hi>Prieſt.</hi> The <hi>Prieſt</hi> himſelfe was <hi>crucified,</hi> the ſacrificer <hi>ſacrificed:</hi> &amp; where <hi>Adam</hi> was buried, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> teſtifieth,<note place="margin">Epiphanius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Kemnitium de Traditio.</note> there was Chriſt on the edge of <hi>Moriah</hi> on <hi>Calvary</hi> crucified. Now the citie is perfitted and <hi>conſummated,</hi> but here <hi>conſummatio conſumptio eſt. Ieruſalem</hi> in her infancy was in a kind of <hi>innocency, Et ſi non Innocentia à peccatis tamen innocentia à ſcandalis, et ſi non libera à peccati ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula, tamen à peccandi malitia.</hi> Shee was a choiſe chaſt virgin, Gods owne <hi>daughter,</hi> nay his <hi>deareling,</hi> as the apple of his <hi>eie</hi> deere vnto him. All his <hi>meſſages</hi> were then endorſed, <hi>Tell the daughter of Syon,</hi> al his Prophets come as <hi>Amos</hi> to <hi>Heſekiah,</hi> the <hi>virgin,</hi> the <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>Syon,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Ieruſalem: Grace</hi> was nurſe to this <hi>virgin</hi> in the time of the <hi>law,</hi> the dew of <hi>Hermon</hi> was her <hi>milke, Melchiſedech,</hi> a King and Prieſt was her <hi>father, David</hi> a King and Prophet was her <hi>foſter father</hi> in her <hi>infancie Ieruſalem</hi> was the <hi>Kings daughter, al glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within, her clothing was of wrought gold, the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Tyre was there with a gift, kings daughters were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong her honourable women, all her garments ſmelt of Mirrh, Aloes, &amp; Caſsia, the King had pleaſure in her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſhe was brought to the King in rayment of needle work, the virgins, that were her fellowes did beare her</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. <hi>Iericho</hi> a Citie of <hi>Palme</hi> trees, <hi>Tyrus</hi> rich in purple, <hi>Samaria</hi> the throne of <hi>Iſrael, Egypt</hi> the womb of <hi>Nilus</hi> &amp; all other <hi>Tributary, ſubſidiary daughters</hi> to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhee was great among the <hi>Nations</hi> and princeſſe of the <hi>provinces.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.</note> The ſunne did once ſhine vpon all the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15625:13"/>reſt of the <hi>world,</hi> yet <hi>Egypt,</hi> only <hi>Egypt</hi> was darke; but now al the reſt of the world was <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>ſun</hi> only ſhined vpon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> There <hi>was no beauty to the beauty of the daughter of Syon,</hi> the Lord kept her as a <hi>match</hi> for his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, ſent many <hi>meſſengers</hi> to her, to <hi>win,</hi> to <hi>wooe</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, but ſhee was turned <hi>harlot</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained <hi>luſt, last</hi> preferred <hi>murther</hi> to the ſervice of <hi>Ieruſalem, murther</hi> ſlew all the <hi>meſſengers</hi> that came: yet God, as deſiring the match, forbare yet to be angry and his prophets <hi>lamented</hi> her: you may heare <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his owne words,<note place="margin">Ier. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>Let mine eies run downe with teares night and day, and let them not ceaſe, for the virgin daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of my people is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a grievous blow. And <hi>Amos</hi> among others, as commiſeratly, <hi>Heare</hi> the lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, O houſe of <hi>Iſrael!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 5.2.</note> O the daughter of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is fallen! And the <hi>lamentations</hi> are ſo ful of <hi>condolements</hi> for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that her <hi>gates</hi> ſunke, her <hi>barres</hi> broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the <hi>ſtones</hi> of her <hi>ſanctuary</hi> ſcattered in every corner in the ſtreet, her <hi>mountaines</hi> deſolate, <hi>houſes</hi> fiered, <hi>temple</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied, <hi>Virgin</hi> violated, and all turned to ruine &amp; <hi>rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> Such are thoſe <hi>lamentations,</hi> that if their <hi>Eccho</hi> can paſſe by the <hi>eares</hi> of any man, and leaue not <hi>lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>paſſion</hi> behinde him, I ſay his hart is a <hi>ſtrong ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle for the divell,</hi> it is harder, then the <hi>nether milſtone.</hi> Well, <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> is <hi>defloured</hi> and <hi>diſfigured, Civitas ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta eſt meretrix, facta eſt adultera,</hi> the <hi>virgin</hi> is turned <hi>whore, civitas ſanctitatis</hi> is become <hi>Civitas ſanguinis,</hi> ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuanus,</hi> The city of peace is become the city of <hi>blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acuanus.</note> the ioy of the <hi>earth</hi> become the ſhame and ſhambles of <hi>the earth,</hi> the <hi>Academy</hi> of the prophets become the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15625:13"/>
               <hi>Aceldama</hi> of the Prophets; <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a lodge in a <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> of <hi>cucumbers,</hi> a <hi>den</hi> of theeues, a <hi>cage</hi> of vncleane birds, the <hi>caue</hi> of vncleane beaſts, habitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where <hi>Zym, Iim, the oſtridge, the ſchritchowle,</hi> the <hi>Satyre</hi> do inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit: yet God continueth his <hi>loue,</hi> and ſends his <hi>ſonne</hi> to this f nfull <hi>City,</hi> and when HE came, ſure hee <hi>loved</hi> her <hi>dearely,</hi> for he wept for her <hi>bitterly:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> but ſhee like a deceitful <hi>harlot</hi> firſt diſſembleth, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betraieth him, one day <hi>kneeleth</hi> before him, the next <hi>accuſeth</hi> him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Pilate,</hi> one day comes to <hi>attend</hi> him with <hi>Palmes</hi> another day gathers to <hi>apprehend</hi> him with <hi>ſtaues,</hi> one day <hi>worſhips</hi> him, another day <hi>crucifies</hi> him. <hi>Hee</hi> that came to preſerue <hi>her,</hi> ſhee goeth about to <hi>deſtroy</hi> him, &amp; preferring him, that <hi>ſlew the living,</hi> before him that <hi>raiſed the dead,</hi> they crucified the Lord of life, <hi>Supplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quo nullum maius! opprobrium quo nullum vilius!<note place="margin">Ratiſbonenſ. de Paſſ. Dom.</note> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> crucified her Saviour <hi>Ieſus:</hi> yet the Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beareth <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> &amp; yet thou remaineſt holy, O thou worſhip of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> When he had been <hi>crucified</hi> and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen againe, and they denyed his <hi>reſurrection,</hi> and he <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendeth</hi> to heaven, and they regard not his <hi>aſcenſion; He,</hi> in his laſt words that <hi>ever</hi> on earth he ſpake to his diſciples <hi>commandeth</hi> them,<note place="margin">Act. 1.4.</note> not to depart from <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> but to wait for the promiſe of the <hi>father,</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> among them in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> I finde ſome of the <hi>ancients</hi> amazed at this loue of the Lorde of life.<note place="margin">Oecum. Theod. in Act Apoſt.</note> Poore diſciples, children of the bride chamber, their eies <hi>ſtreaming</hi> with <hi>teares</hi> &amp; <hi>harts</hi> breaking with <hi>ſighes,</hi> muſt they yet continue in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> With that <hi>ſinfull nation, that people laden with iniquity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.</note> 
               <hi>ſeed of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15625:14"/>wicked corrupt children,</hi> with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had ſo provoked the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to anger: why not in <hi>Ephrata?</hi> where the Lord was born, why not in <hi>Galily?</hi> whence they were choſen. Of all places, why in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> the moſt <hi>odious</hi> of al places, in murdrous, adulterous <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſtained with <hi>blood,</hi> &amp; for ever <hi>branded</hi> with the <hi>ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> of treaſon againſt her <hi>Lord:</hi> why in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which all the <hi>Prophets,</hi> had ſhot of vollies of <hi>wo,</hi> and <hi>heaven</hi> ſent downe thunderbolts of <hi>vengeance:</hi> why in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> where they were as <hi>odious,</hi> as <hi>obvious</hi> to <hi>Herods</hi> Court, <hi>Pilats</hi> pleading place, to <hi>Phariſees, ſouldiers,</hi> to al, that were famous for infamy. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> had been ſlaine, <hi>Iohn Faptiſt</hi> murdred, and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> crucified in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> what leſſe, could they <hi>here</hi> expect? <hi>the diſciple is not aboue his Maſter,</hi> it had beene <hi>hatefull,</hi> and how could it be leſſe then <hi>hateful,</hi> to them, to be in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> I omit many reaſons; moſt of the Greek fathers differing herein,<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Act. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>noluit Chriſtus equos ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> auriga prodire, Oecumenius</hi> giving another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: <hi>ne ſi citò digreſſi eſsent reſurrectionis Chriſti veritas eſſet ſuſpecta,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oecumen. in Act <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Oecumenius. Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Micah</hi> giue a better reaſon,<note place="margin">Eſ. 2 3.</note> 
               <hi>de Syon exibit lex &amp; verbum Domini de Ieruſalem,</hi> it was not the <hi>city,</hi> or <hi>ſeat,</hi> or <hi>ſight</hi> of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> though the <hi>loftineſse</hi> of the <hi>ſituatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, temperature,</hi> and <hi>moderation</hi> of the <hi>heaven, fruitfulnes</hi> of the <hi>ſoile,</hi> all be honored &amp; ſo mentioned by <hi>Ioſephus, Strabo, Pliny, Tacitus,</hi> though it was <hi>totius terrae vmbilicus,</hi> the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and very verticall point of the whole earth, <hi>in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Natura omnes vires eſſudiſſet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livy.</note> as <hi>Hormiſda</hi> ſpake of <hi>Rome.</hi> Yet al this is not the cauſe of their <hi>ſlay,</hi> or of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15625:14"/>
               <hi>ſcriptures</hi> honouring, of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but becauſe, it was the <hi>place,</hi> to which the <hi>covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> was made, that hence the word of the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſhould paſſe into al <hi>lands,</hi> it was the <hi>type,</hi> &amp; <hi>repreſentation</hi> of the elect Church of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> It was the <hi>place</hi> of Gods <hi>ſervice,</hi> the temple of <hi>ſacrifice</hi> the houſe of <hi>praier,</hi> the conſecrated holy <hi>place</hi> of the moſt <hi>high.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Parallel</hi> of the Church, &amp; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> being meaſured with <hi>Ezechiels</hi> line, we ſhall finde, that as <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was built on a <hi>rocke,</hi> ſo the <hi>Church</hi> vpon Chriſt the <hi>rocke:</hi> as <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was ſurrou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>hils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comp Ieruſal. cum Eccleſia ex quam plurimis Rabbinis.</note> ſo the Church compaſſed with Gods <hi>protection: Ieruſalem</hi> could not be conquered from the <hi>Jebuſites,</hi> but by <hi>David,</hi> nor the church redeemed from <hi>Satan</hi> and ſinne but by <hi>Chriſt: Iudah</hi> the ſeede of bleere eied <hi>Leah,</hi> inhabiting of the one ſide, ſignifi's the <hi>church</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles, Beniamin</hi> the fruit of faire <hi>Rahel,</hi> on the other <hi>ſide</hi> the hill <hi>Moriah</hi> figureth the church of the <hi>Iews:</hi> both had a part in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> both belong to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> built on the <hi>South,</hi> had the ſun moſt <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> ſhining therein, the <hi>church</hi> hath the ſonne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, moſt gloriouſly illuminating it: <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the viſion of <hi>peace,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> the family of <hi>peace:</hi> All the <hi>Tribes</hi> came to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> all nations come vnto the <hi>Church:</hi> in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was the continual worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> the continued <hi>ſervice</hi> of God: here he was more particularly, not only <hi>per eſſentiam,</hi> as hee is in all <hi>creatures,</hi> or <hi>per potentiam,</hi> as he is even in hel, <hi>ſed per reſidentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith <hi>Altenſteg;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alt enſteg. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> &amp; this cauſed the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> ſo much to recall, and <hi>record,</hi> the <hi>remembrance</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Which leadeth to this <hi>poſition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Doct,</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Religion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15625:15"/>only is that, which addeth grace and honour to place a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion,</hi> as the heathen confeſſeth, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is not only the band betwixt man and man,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> the knot of all <hi>communion,</hi> and <hi>conſociation,</hi> but is the ſweet <hi>ointment,</hi> and holy ornament of the <hi>place,</hi> where it is. <hi>Shiloa,</hi> is honoured for the poole of <hi>Shiloa,</hi> but more for that the Tabernacle ſtood in <hi>Shiloa. Bethel</hi> is honoured for the Well of which <hi>David</hi> deſired the water, but much more for that <hi>Chriſt</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> was borne there. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> honored for her <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> but much more for the <hi>worſhip of God,</hi> in the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> For the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in the Acts, as <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, came not to ſee the <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple</hi> but to performe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in <hi>Ierulalem.</hi> And while this worſhip continued, God called <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. in. Act.</note> 
               <hi>Domus mea,</hi> but when this fire was gone out, <hi>Domus veſtra.</hi> Syon is my hill, ſaith the <hi>Lord, Ieruſalem</hi> my city, the Temple <hi>Domus mea:</hi> but when <hi>they</hi> forſooke him, <hi>he</hi> forſooke them, when their <hi>Religion</hi> expired, he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>departed,</hi> they change the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, he forſook the <hi>patronage:</hi> it was <hi>Domus mea,</hi> now <hi>Domus veſtra,</hi> once <hi>Domus mea, per amoris antiquitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> now <hi>Domus veſtra, per peccati iniquitatem,</hi> as a <hi>Gloſſe</hi> noteth now when the <hi>life</hi> of their <hi>liues,</hi> and blood of their <hi>ſoules,</hi> Religion ceaſed, it is become <hi>Loruhamah, Loamint, Domus veſtra, a den of theeues.</hi> Fearefull is that place of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>if any man draw backe, my ſoule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was borne in <hi>Bethlehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> annointed in <hi>Bethlehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> yet hee preferreth <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in his ſong: it did reioice
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15625:15"/>
               <hi>him,</hi> when they went to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that his feet might ſtand in thy gates <hi>O Ieruſalem.</hi> O pray for the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> let them proſper, that loue thee, <hi>Peace</hi> bee within thy <hi>wals, plenteouſneſſe</hi> within thy palaces. The <hi>honour</hi> of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> in <hi>Micah</hi> is much, <hi>thou Bethlehem Ephrata, though thou be litle amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the thouſands of Iudah, yet out of thee he ſhall come forth vnto me, that is to be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in Iſrael.</hi> Obſerue the continuance, and perpetuity of honour, done to little <hi>Bethel:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 5.25.</note> The 1 covenant made by God to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 12.8.</note> &amp; the firſt altar made by <hi>Abraham</hi> to God was in <hi>Bethel.</hi> Neere the ſame place <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſonne built his firſt altar, and the Lord firſt appeared here to <hi>Iſaac.</hi> In the ſame <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.24.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob</hi> his ſonne recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his viſion, God maketh his covenant with him. In the ſame <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.20.</note> God commands <hi>Iacob</hi> to build him an altar, &amp; here Iacob giueth it that name the houſe of God. In the ſame <hi>Bethel, David</hi> of the line of <hi>Iacob</hi> was borne, &amp; annointed, and in the ſame <hi>Bethel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 35.15. 1. Sam. 16.</note> now the city of <hi>David,</hi> was Chriſt, of the ſeed of <hi>David,</hi> borne. Loe, thus ſhall bee done to the place, that the Lord doth <hi>honor,</hi> thus ſhal be done to the place where God his name is <hi>called</hi> vpon. It is not the <hi>loftineſſe</hi> of the building, the <hi>aſpiring</hi> of the towres, the <hi>multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie</hi> of their turrets, the <hi>ſeats</hi> of iudgement, houſes of the <hi>High Prieſts, ſchools of the Prophets, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cknes</hi> of their ſenced vault round about the <hi>city,</hi> in which were one hundred and fiftie thouſand men, which <hi>Strabo</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to be two <hi>hundred,</hi> &amp; <hi>fiftie</hi> paces, nor thoſe 400 catechiſing houſes, which the <hi>Ribbins</hi> mention in the city, nor the <hi>Palaces</hi> of the Princes, nor the ſepulchre
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15625:16"/>of their kings, nor the 11 orders of the city, or the 9 <hi>fountaines,</hi> or 12 <hi>gates,</hi> or ninetie <hi>turrets,</hi> which <hi>Villal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pand</hi> deſcribeth,<note place="margin">Villal. in Ezek.</note> or the <hi>mountaines</hi> aboue it, or <hi>valleyes</hi> about <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> no not the <hi>Temple</hi> it ſelfe, that was 7 yeares building by the dayly labour of a hundred fifty three thouſand men: but it was the worſhip of God, <hi>Religion</hi> that gaue the grace &amp; <hi>countenance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſephus.</note> that made it the golden head of the <hi>picture; Lady</hi> of the world, <hi>ſeate</hi> of the Monarchy, <hi>Virgin</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt, ioy</hi> of the earth, ſo deare to our <hi>Prophet,</hi> as that he cryeth out, If J <hi>forget thee O Ieruſalem, then let my hand forget her cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> A <hi>Doctrine,</hi> that ſhould be as <hi>fearefull</hi> for <hi>terrifying,</hi> as <hi>powerfull</hi> for <hi>inſtructing,</hi> all thoſe places, &amp; perſons, that the Lord hath <hi>bleſſed,</hi> by placing his <hi>name,</hi> &amp; <hi>word</hi> among them. <hi>Tyrus</hi> Purple, or <hi>Iericho's</hi> Palmes, or <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mariahs</hi> kings, or <hi>Ninivehs buildings,</hi> continue not; <hi>Canker</hi> and <hi>Corruption</hi> hath vtterly conſumed them, not a <hi>ſtone remaining on a ſtone,</hi> they are forſaken, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by them <hi>Religion</hi> is forſaken. <hi>Quinzay</hi> in the eaſt, <hi>Mexico</hi> in the weſt, <hi>Millaine</hi> as it is, <hi>Antwerpe</hi> as it was, <hi>Paris</hi> in her late glory, <hi>Venice</hi> in her now beauty, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not continue, becauſe <hi>Religion</hi> continueth not. The prime <hi>city</hi> of this land, the <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>kingdome,</hi> and chamber of the <hi>king,</hi> hath beene often ſwept, her fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation hath beene ſhaken, the multitude of her <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> hath conſumed multitudes of her <hi>inhabitants,</hi> and that <hi>Nabuchadonoſor,</hi> the plague hath kept viſitation in her,<note place="margin">Senec. Trag.</note> 
               <hi>Iuveneſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſenibus coniungens, &amp; gnatis patres fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſta peſtis,</hi> and why haue theſe ecclipſes often hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15625:16"/>the ſunſhine of her <hi>Citizens,</hi> but for their neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of <hi>Religion.</hi> Wherfore my <hi>beloued,</hi> ſeeing that <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> this day maketh a <hi>proclamation</hi> vnto you, as wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> entertain her, let her be the <hi>bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celet, tablet, frontlet,</hi> of each Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the names of the great ones ſhall <hi>rot,</hi> their <hi>bodies</hi> rot on the earth,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.</note> and their <hi>ſoules</hi> rot in <hi>Sheol,</hi> and their memories rot amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the poſterities, thy <hi>name</hi> to thy <hi>poſterity,</hi> if thou be religious, ſhal be a happy <hi>patrimonie. David</hi> is more honoured in Scripture for being a <hi>Prophet</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>King, Solomon</hi> more regarded for being a <hi>preacher</hi> then a <hi>Prince,</hi> Job not honoured for his <hi>Camels,</hi> his <hi>ſheepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> his <hi>oxen,</hi> his <hi>riches,</hi> but becauſe he was a <hi>righteous man. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> religion and obedience, gat him the title of <hi>father of the faithfull:</hi> military men may remember the faith &amp; religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> honored not for his band or <hi>command,</hi> that he had power to bid one <hi>come</hi> and he came, another goe, &amp; he <hi>went,</hi> but for his <hi>word, non ſum dignus. Citizens</hi> and <hi>Towneſmen</hi> may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by <hi>Symon</hi> the <hi>Tanner, Courtiers</hi> by the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, women by <hi>Lydia,</hi> young men by <hi>Titus,</hi> ſervants by <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> who ever thou art, thou art not left <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable,</hi> ô man, examples, precepts, bleſſings for the practiſe, curſes for the neglect of religion, are offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red dayly to thy <hi>meditation.</hi> The <hi>praiſes</hi> of Religion ſhould not only incite, but <hi>aſtoniſh</hi> thee, <hi>Kings her nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing fathers, Queenes her nurſing mothers;</hi> for louelines ſhee is a <hi>Roe,</hi> for fruitfulneſſe a <hi>vine,</hi> for holyneſſe a <hi>prieſthood,</hi> for brightnes the <hi>morning,</hi> for ſafetie mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Syon,</hi> for Royaltie a <hi>Queene,</hi> for beautie the <hi>Sunne,</hi> for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15625:17"/>
               <hi>priviledges,</hi> the <hi>godly</hi> and religious in themſelues, they be bleſſed in the <hi>citie,</hi> bleſſed in the <hi>field,</hi> bleſſed in the fruit of the body,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> bleſſed in the <hi>fruit</hi> of the ground, in the fruit of the <hi>cattell,</hi> in the increaſe of the <hi>kine,</hi> &amp; in the flocks of <hi>ſheepe,</hi> bleſſed in the <hi>basket,</hi> and the ſtore, bleſſed, when thy <hi>goe</hi> in, and when they goe out, and <hi>bleſſed</hi> in every thing they ſhall put to their hand. For their <hi>Family,</hi> and the preſervation thereof, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands ſhall fal before him, tenne <hi>thouſandes</hi> at his right hand, it ſhall not come nigh him, no evill ſhall come neere his dwelling. For his <hi>children,</hi> the ſeed of the <hi>righteous</hi> is bleſſed, I haue beene young, ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>now am old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 37.</note> 
               <hi>yet</hi> I <hi>never ſaw the righteous forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or his ſeed begging their bread.</hi> Marke this yee <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, yee,</hi> to whom, your <hi>children,</hi> be as deere as your <hi>liues,</hi> yee whoſe whole <hi>life</hi> is only for the continuance of your <hi>poſterity,</hi> yee, whoſe long <hi>travels,</hi> troubled <hi>meales,</hi> ſhort <hi>ſleepes,</hi> great <hi>cares,</hi> nay great <hi>ſinnes</hi> be only to maintaine your <hi>name</hi> and family, let <hi>Religion</hi> be the foundation, <hi>godlineſſe</hi> the gaine, <hi>ſanctitie</hi> the <hi>legacy</hi> you bequeath to your <hi>children,</hi> no <hi>moth</hi> ſhall corrupt it, no <hi>theefe</hi> ſhall ſteale it, no Pyonerlike <hi>advocate</hi> ſhal <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> it, your <hi>generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſhal remain amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the <hi>poſterity.</hi> Let <hi>Religion,</hi> be the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of their <hi>childhood,</hi> the <hi>guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> of their <hi>youth,</hi> and then it will be the <hi>guide</hi> of their <hi>age,</hi> the <hi>garland</hi> of their <hi>life,</hi> and their good <hi>Angel</hi> to glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At alia eſt religio Iudaeorum, alia Samaritanorum, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia Gentium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome, Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> had a <hi>temple,</hi> but <hi>Samaria</hi> a <hi>groue, Bethel</hi> an <hi>Idol,</hi> how is the true <hi>religion</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15625:17"/>to be knowne, men cry here is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> there is <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I anſwere firſt with <hi>Ieremy</hi> 6.16. ſtand vpon the waies, be hold and aske for the old way, that is the good way,<note place="margin">Ierem. 6.16.</note> walke therein, and yee ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules. <hi>Per Scripturam etenim Deus loquitur omnia quae vult,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> ſaith <hi>Gregory:</hi> ſecondly <hi>avoide</hi> that <hi>way,</hi> which <hi>deviſeth</hi> to keepe thee in <hi>ignorance,</hi> that is a godleſſe religion, devout impiety; buy the <hi>truth,</hi> and ſell it not, let only that, which ſcripture teacheth, <hi>evince</hi> thy conſcience, <hi>convince</hi> thy vnderſtanding.<note place="margin">Aug. cont. Dona</note> It was holy <hi>Auguſtines</hi> poſition, <hi>audi non quid Donatus, aut Vincentius, aut Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus, aut Hilarius, ſed quid dicit Dominus,</hi> be deſirous to <hi>heare,</hi> carefull to <hi>proue,</hi> faithfull to <hi>retaine,</hi> that is truth: ſo thou ſhalt be <hi>bleſſed,</hi> if thou be thus, the <hi>religious</hi> man, that feareth <hi>the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At in Ieruſalem Chriſtus ipſe à proditore proditus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boſq. de Tempt</note> why but there is no ſuch <hi>priviledge</hi> to <hi>place,</hi> to <hi>time,</hi> to <hi>perſon,</hi> but there may be an <hi>ecclipſe,</hi> and even the <hi>beſt ſighted vnderſtanding,</hi> may faile to finde by <hi>outwarde reaſon,</hi> the <hi>inward power</hi> of religion, <hi>for perſon</hi> the moſt ſacred, the worlds <hi>Saviour</hi> was <hi>tempted,</hi> for <hi>place</hi> not only in the <hi>deſert,</hi> but on the pinnacle of the <hi>Temple,</hi> for <hi>time</hi> not only when he <hi>faſted,</hi> but after the greateſt <hi>feaſt,</hi> that ever he kept, for he was betrayed at <hi>the paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over.</hi> I deny not <hi>Beloved,</hi> but when that the children <hi>of God,</hi> came to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, before the Lord, <hi>Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> alſo came to preſent himſelfe; when the whole world, had but ſo many <hi>perſons</hi> as it hath <hi>parts,</hi> but 4. there was a <hi>Cain,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there were, after the flood but 8. there was a <hi>Cham, Lucifer</hi> among <hi>Angels, Iudas</hi> among <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15625:18"/>Nicolas</hi> among <hi>Deacons:</hi> I know that in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> a <hi>ſnake</hi> may lurke, and in <hi>Samaria,</hi> when the Church was eſtabliſhed, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> appeareth, even in all <hi>ages,</hi> there wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted not a <hi>Demas,</hi> a <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> ſome agent for the <hi>Divell,</hi> to betray <hi>religion,</hi> ſome that <hi>ſow with ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſeed, plough with an oxe and aſſe, weare garments of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſtuffes, worſhip at Salem,</hi> and yet ſacrifice at <hi>Sheche<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> who with blended, doubled, poiſoned harts, do in theſe or the like holy <hi>places</hi> come with <hi>old ſcraps,</hi> as the <hi>Gibeo nites</hi> deceived with <hi>oldſhooes,</hi> who being <hi>vngrounded</hi> in their firſt <hi>elements</hi> of <hi>learning,</hi> proue vnſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,</hi> and rotten in <hi>Divinity,</hi> be ever <hi>learning,</hi> &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to the <hi>knowledge of the truth.</hi> If ever there were any ſuch <hi>moates</hi> or <hi>mothes</hi> about the Candle of this place, I wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to conſider the feareful ſtory of thoſe two falſe Prophets in the time of <hi>Ieremiah. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naniah</hi> and <hi>Shemaiah</hi> did both <hi>Prophecy</hi> to the people, neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for <hi>Baals</hi> prophets, yet both, ſaith the holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> did propehcy <hi>lyes,</hi> the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon <hi>Hananiah</hi> is Ier. 28.16. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I will cast thee of, from the face of the earth, this yeare thou ſhalt die, becauſe thou haſt lied against the Lord. Against Shemaiah the iudgement is pronounced,</hi> Ier. 29.32. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, becauſe Shemaiah hath prophecyed, and I ſent him not, and he cauſed them to trust in a lie, I will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Shemaiah and his ſeed, he ſhall not haue a man to dwell among this people for ever.</hi> Bleſſed be the Lord! that ſo harty &amp; holy is the <hi>Iealouſie</hi> of vs for <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that now we may ſay inverting <hi>Gregories</hi> words, <hi>Tinea ſoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fecit damnum non fecit,</hi> though the mothe made
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15625:18"/>ſome <hi>ſound,</hi> yet it left no <hi>ſoile,</hi> and is now ſilenced; we may ſay as <hi>Augustine</hi> diſcourſing vpon him, who in the time of Chriſts betraying fled naked, and left his <hi>linnen</hi> garment behinde him, <hi>certè hic non diſcipulus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diog. Laert. in vit. Biantis.</note> ſure this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the <hi>diſciples,</hi> or as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſpake ſuch were (as <hi>Bias</hi> ſpake of ſailers, <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inter vivos nec mortuos</hi>) with vs but not of vs, and ſuch baſtard Eagles dare not endure the ſun-ſhine of <hi>ſcripture,</hi> no marvaile then, <hi>quia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, qui in vita perfidi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>in doctrina infidi:</hi> falſe <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpeaking <hi>Aſhdod</hi> and <hi>hebrew,</hi> falſe <hi>Balamites</hi> that curſe &amp; bleſſe, falſe <hi>Ephramites</hi> bak'd on one ſide, dough on the other, falſe <hi>Grecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> neither faith full to <hi>Achilles</hi> nor <hi>Hector,</hi> falſe <hi>Laodiceans</hi> neither hot nor cold. And again; Bleſſed be the name of our God, that as that <hi>honourable</hi> mother, and fruitfull twin our ſiſter <hi>Cambridge,</hi> may reioice in the happy fruit of her <hi>wombe;</hi> ſo we in thoſe many in all ages ſince Popery firſt <hi>engaſtered</hi> religion, who nobly haue reſiſted it, &amp; haue nobly run all the ſunnes courſe, with more light then the ſunne, as <hi>Groſthead, Wickliffe, Bradwarden, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, Scotus, Occam, Iewell, Humfreys, Rainolds, Hooker, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> our many worthies now among vs, &amp; the <hi>ſunne</hi> &amp; <hi>moon</hi> of our preſent church gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thoſe peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>vnparalleld Biſhops.</hi> And the religion that this our <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> hath ever maintained, is that <hi>Religion,</hi> which not only <hi>Sleidan</hi> calleth Proteſtant,<note place="margin">Sleid. Com. Augad Bon. com. ep. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> but even that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> calleth Proteſtant religion; his words be plaine, <hi>ad Bonifacium Comitem, de coercendis haereticis,</hi> where he calleth the <hi>religion</hi> of his time by the name of ours, <hi>proteſtationem Catholicorum,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15625:19"/>
               <hi>religion</hi> of the <hi>Catholickes,</hi> which ought to bee as deere to <hi>vs,</hi> as ever <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was to <hi>David.</hi> But, I haue kept you too long in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> yet I was to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the commande, of the <hi>Prophet,</hi> walke about <hi>Syon,</hi> go round about her, tel the <hi>Towres</hi> thereof marke well her <hi>bullwarkes,</hi> conſider her <hi>palaces,</hi> and tell it to them, that come after. I will now lead you out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Angell did <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> and I will quickly meaſure out the reſt that <hi>remaineth; elſe let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">part. </seg>3</label> I muſt not lead you through a <hi>library</hi> of interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, whether <hi>Dextra</hi> be Chriſt, as <hi>Lyranus,</hi> or <hi>vita aeterna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyra, Carth. Moler. in Pſal.</note> as <hi>Carthuſian,</hi> or <hi>opera virtutis</hi> as the gloſſe, or <hi>divinum auxilium</hi> as <hi>Mollerus,</hi> the ſumme of all is, the ſenſe of all, all one, he wiſheth <hi>knowledge and mercy</hi> to forſake him, if he forget <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Jt was not a <hi>worde blowne</hi> from his <hi>lips</hi> &amp; <hi>lungs,</hi> but his <hi>bowels</hi> did yearne, and his very <hi>inwards</hi> did yeeld, his ſoule ſent out, with extraordinary vehemency, this holy and hearty <hi>impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Innocentius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lor. in Pſ.</note> bringeth 7. notions of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the <hi>hand, pro filio dei, potentia, gratia, auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, protectione, operatione, vindicta:</hi> The <hi>Opticks</hi> honour the <hi>eie,</hi> the <hi>Romaines</hi> the <hi>hand;</hi> it is the whole bodies <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent,</hi> it is the <hi>ſenſorium</hi> of the <hi>touch</hi> only, but the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme and <hi>reſemblance</hi> of fiue ſeverall ſenſes and their <hi>faculties. Obliviſcatur aextra;</hi> doth he wiſh himſelfe to looſe his right hand? <hi>vehementer certè ſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtringit, atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer ſe obligavit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi> on this Pſal. The loſſe of the <hi>right</hi> vſe of the <hi>right</hi> hand,<note place="margin">Auſt. in Pſ. 117.</note> whether yee take it for the loſſe of <hi>mercy</hi> as <hi>Acuanus,</hi> or the loſſe of protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15625:19"/>as <hi>Albinus,</hi> or the loſſe of cunning, or skill, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as <hi>Mollerus</hi> on this Pſalme. Surely the loſſe of the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in a ſpiritual ſenſe is a curſe: the greateſt curſe, that <hi>David could wiſh his enemy is, that Sathan might stand at his right hand</hi> Pſal. 109.6. <hi>And the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test imprecation</hi> againſt himſelfe is,<note place="margin">Pſ. 109.</note> that his <hi>right hande may forget her cunning.</hi> The <hi>divers gifts,</hi> that God hath beſtowed vpon the <hi>ſons of men,</hi> enabling them in <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge</hi> to excell, bee to be <hi>eſteemed,</hi> their author to bee <hi>acknowledged,</hi> their excellence to be <hi>admired,</hi> and their end to be imployed to the glory of the <hi>giuer,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe men haue the right hand, and not the vſe of the <hi>right hand.</hi> Hee that abuſeth his <hi>knowledge,</hi> his right hand, like the hand of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> will wither, <hi>knowledge</hi> then flouriſheth, when <hi>diligence</hi> planteth it, and <hi>grace</hi> watereth it, then God giveth the <hi>encreaſe.</hi> Of all the trees in Paradiſe, the moſt principall was the tree of <hi>knowledge,</hi> knowledge is the <hi>fiery pillar</hi> to lead vs through the <hi>wilderneſſe</hi> of our <hi>wills,</hi> it is the <hi>Manna</hi> of the <hi>worlds</hi> deſert, the <hi>beacon</hi> in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, the <hi>Lamp</hi> in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Cyprian</hi> complaineth <hi>ad Demetrium, Indies deficit in agris agricola, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp. ad Demet.</note> There is a dayly <hi>defection</hi> of all knowledge, in the <hi>husbandman</hi> in the <hi>field,</hi> the <hi>marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> at the <hi>ſea,</hi> innocency in the <hi>Court,</hi> iuſtice in <hi>iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> workmanſhip in <hi>trades,</hi> diſcipline in <hi>ſchooles.</hi> All theſe faile, and will vaniſh like <hi>ſmoke,</hi> &amp; wither like the graſſe, vntill they be <hi>directed</hi> to their true end &amp; <hi>ſcope,</hi> the ſervice of God, which maketh plaine this <hi>poſition, That, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> that knowledge, which is not imployed to Gods glory, is liable to a curſe, and ſhall periſh.</hi> There is a <hi>worme</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15625:20"/>that <hi>Palme,</hi> a <hi>northwind</hi> ſhall blaſt it, it is like the ſpiders neſt in <hi>Iob;</hi> it is a <hi>Meteor,</hi> a <hi>Cloud,</hi> an <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> a <hi>Cymbalum tinniens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 9. 1. Cor. 15.</note> a well without <hi>water,</hi> a curſe, not a bleſſing to the <hi>poſſeſsions</hi> thereof, and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume away as a moth fretting a garment, as the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>timely fruit of a woman, it ſhall never ſee the ſunne. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> found this true,<note place="margin">1. King. 10.</note> that <hi>angelicall</hi> and bleſſed harmonie of muſicke, <hi>conſecrated</hi> by <hi>David,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by <hi>Solomon,</hi> continued till the deportation into <hi>Babylon,</hi> was loſt in <hi>Babylon,</hi> never returned againe they ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vp their harps, but never took the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe, this <hi>imprecation</hi> fell vpon them, <hi>verè ſic contigit,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> on this Pſalme,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod optavit, praenunciavit,</hi> their right hand forgot her cunning, their <hi>harpes</hi> and <hi>Pipes, Lutes, Trumpets, Cymbals,</hi> their well <hi>tuned,</hi> lowd <hi>ſounding Cymball,</hi> never returned againe, the voice of <hi>muſicall</hi> reioycing was never heard again in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, <hi>&amp; ſie peribit omnis ſcientia quae cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> à Deo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambroſ. Ep.</note> 
               <hi>ad Deum non recedit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> A <hi>Doctrine</hi> moſt fit for this <hi>place</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> &amp; neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerneth vs all, who by the <hi>mercy of God,</hi> and the bleſſing of our <hi>honourable mother</hi> the Vniverſitie, at this time, how vnworthily our ſoules beſt know haue receaued encouragement, for our proceeding in <hi>knowledge, virtue,</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe</hi> of <hi>living,</hi> how many or how few ſoever our talents be, that wee make the beſt of them for the <hi>good of the Church,</hi> and the glory of our God. It is ever obſerued, that the children of darknes, are wiſer in their generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of light, I meane the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> who as if by ſome <hi>monopoly</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15625:20"/>or <hi>impropriation</hi> they had challenged, all <hi>learning</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> to themſelues, are ſo earneſt &amp; forwarde in their ſtudies, that they blind &amp; beſot the world with an <hi>eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> of them, as if the <hi>tree of knowledge</hi> grew only in their <hi>gardens:</hi> whereas the <hi>gleanings</hi> of <hi>Ephraim</hi> are farre better then the <hi>vintage of Abiezer,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> themſelues, are but the <hi>Collectors for the poore,</hi> and as if they made no <hi>conſcience</hi> of that commandement, <hi>thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> they cunningly haue purloined whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is good in them, out of our <hi>men.</hi> Jt is an ancient complaint that they had their <hi>Hebrew</hi> from <hi>Reuclin, Greeke</hi> from <hi>Budaeus, Latin</hi> from <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> &amp; that<note n="*" place="margin">As hath beene proved by bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed D. Rainolds, Keckerman, and others.</note> 
               <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavincentius</hi> hath ſtolne a whole Tract from <hi>Hyperius,</hi> and printed it in his owne name. What is <hi>there,</hi> in the whole <hi>Bulke</hi> of voluminous <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> but that which he hath heaped vp out of <hi>Kemnitius, Calvin, Iewell?</hi> what hath <hi>Lorinus</hi> in his large, rather <hi>painefull,</hi> then <hi>faithfull,</hi> Commentaries, but what our hiues &amp; helps for interpretation haue afforded him? What hath <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> in his Mathematicks, but that which <hi>Melancthou,</hi> or moſt of them, for their method but what <hi>Ramus</hi> hath delivered them? To vſe <hi>Bonaventure</hi> his words in the preface <hi>Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bard</hi> to, <hi>Compilatores ſunt non authores:</hi> yet this I ſay their <hi>induſtry</hi> muſt edge ours, if, they doe the <hi>Divell</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> ſuch diligent <hi>ſervice,</hi> how <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> ſhould we be, to pleaſe our <hi>God.</hi> An <hi>illiterate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> there is in ſome, not only to neglect, but conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the vſe of <hi>arts and ſciences,</hi> I am ſure our <hi>Prophet</hi> did it not, nor his <hi>ſonne,</hi> who was ſo <hi>ſkilfull</hi> though a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that he wrote of all <hi>creatures,</hi> from the <hi>Cedar</hi> to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15625:21"/>the <hi>Hiſſope</hi> on the wals. <hi>Worthy</hi> was that ſaying of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randula, ſi turpe ſit bonas liter as colere, mallem agnoſcere quàm deprecari culpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> If it be an opprobrious thing, to embrace <hi>good letters,</hi> I had rather acknowlege my <hi>fault,</hi> then aſke <hi>pardon,</hi> for it. Jt is worthily obſerved by one of the glorious lights of our Church, that <hi>Moyſes</hi> was learned in the wiſdome of Egypt, <hi>Daniel</hi> skilfull in the knowledge of <hi>Chaldea, Iob</hi> not vnexpert in <hi>Aſtronomy, Ieremy</hi> skilfull in the common <hi>lawes</hi> of his time, <hi>David</hi> in muſicke, <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Poetry,</hi> and in all the <hi>knowledge</hi> both of <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp; thoſe holy <hi>Martyrs,</hi> &amp; fathers, the great <hi>lights</hi> of the <hi>firmament, Cyprian, Auſtin, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> and the reſt, haue come laden out of <hi>Egypt</hi> with the treaſures, and ſpoiles of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> inſtructed for the better <hi>ſervice</hi> of God with <hi>helpe</hi> of <hi>ſciences</hi> and prophane <hi>learning:</hi> and therefore they are to be <hi>pitied</hi> rather then envied, <hi>qui ſuae patrocinantur ignorantiae,</hi> faith <hi>Eraſmus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſm. ſcholia in Ier. ad Pam. Bucer. Aemil. Prob. loc. <hi>151.</hi> Pomer. in <hi>1.</hi> ad Cor. <hi>2.</hi> Cal in <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>plus inſcitiâ ſuâ fidunt &amp; ſuperbiunt quàm alij eruditione ſuâ,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bucer, rudes et degeneres ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pomeranus,</hi> nay <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Calvine</hi> is ſo abſolute for this, as that his words vpon the 15. of the 1. Cor. are, <hi>Colligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hos eſse ſuperſtitioſos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>beloved,</hi> all you of the yonger ſort, that are to be flowriſhing plants, in particular <hi>ſocieties,</hi> or are to be <hi>tranſplanted</hi> from this <hi>Eden</hi> of God, and to paſſe into the <hi>functions</hi> and <hi>Sanctions</hi> either of <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common</hi> weale; firſt ſtay at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> til the ſpirit be ſent you. The gift of <hi>tongues,</hi> was only given at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> it is <hi>morbus comitialis,</hi> that at our proceedings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt or ſecond degree ſome moſt rude, thinke
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15625:21"/>themſelues moſt ripe, and forſake the Vniverſity ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to returne againe. I ſay againe, ſo long as God, &amp; friends &amp; any meanes may be had, ſtay at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> till the ſpirit be ſent you. When you go <hi>hence,</hi> take <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> with you, exerciſe your <hi>talent,</hi> to the honour of your <hi>Maſter,</hi> that the retributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be, <hi>good &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant, thou haſte been faithfull in a little, I will make thee ruler over much.</hi> Otherwiſe, <hi>your right hand ſhal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honourable <hi>Lawyers,</hi> I giue you but that title, that your own glorious <hi>Emperour</hi> gaue you, how ever, the <hi>fat kine</hi> haue eaten vp the <hi>leane,</hi> and the <hi>law</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt devoured your <hi>law:</hi> yet in your <hi>knowledge,</hi> which is more <hi>honoured</hi> in al parts of the <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> then is our <hi>owne land,</hi> let it be <hi>ſeene,</hi> that your <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> turn to the <hi>good,</hi> not the <hi>diſgrace</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> Church &amp; <hi>Churchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> haue <hi>enimies</hi> more then <hi>friends.</hi> If a poore Prophet or <hi>Levite</hi> came before the <hi>Doctors</hi> of the <hi>law,</hi> among the Phariſees, the word was, <hi>Goe in peace:</hi> Jf ever you come to place of <hi>authority,</hi> and a poore <hi>Miniſter</hi> come before you, let him haue <hi>counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> far be it, that your <hi>learned lawes</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſnares</hi> to good <hi>minds,</hi> or <hi>quirks</hi> for mercenary <hi>wits: lex et pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae,</hi> your <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> are ever ioined in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> divide not, <hi>divorce</hi> them not, <hi>leaſt</hi> your right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forget her cunning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Learned,</hi> and Honourable <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> I giue you that title, that the ſon of <hi>Sirach</hi> giveth, it is but <hi>Apocrhypha;</hi> direct your knowledge, the right hand of your <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> to the <hi>right vſe;</hi> let <hi>praier</hi> go before, <hi>Religion</hi> bee
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15625:22"/>an ingredient in al your practiſe, let it not be obſerved as <hi>Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius</hi> once ſaid, and yet in ſome places, though not here, yet in the great city of this land is frequently &amp; lamentably to be found that <hi>dum corpus medici refici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt aegrotorum animas inficiunt,</hi> that while <hi>irreligious, Ephraimiticall, Hypocriticall,</hi> popiſh <hi>Phyſitians</hi> cure the body, by ſome <hi>Idolatrous</hi> dram, they infect the <hi>ſoules of their vnhappy</hi> rather them <hi>vnhealthy patients.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>donum ſanationis</hi> was given only to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> practiſe with <hi>care,</hi> with <hi>knowledge,</hi> with <hi>conſcience, leſt your right hand forget her cunning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>deere,</hi> and Reverend <hi>brethren</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> you know what your <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſaid, be yee not called <hi>Doctors</hi> for there is but one <hi>Doctor</hi> which is Chriſt, that is, <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Iunius</hi> giving allowance to this interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be not <hi>Phariſaicall</hi> Doctors, neither idle, nor idol Doctors, not <hi>factious,</hi> not <hi>ambitious,</hi> for otherwiſe, <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit Christus alios Doctores, alios Pastores, alios Prophets in Eccleſia,</hi> though the painted <hi>Phariſees of this age</hi> envy you this <hi>honorable</hi> degree. The contempt we are liable vnto is much, even by thoſe <hi>whoſe fathers,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> I would not place <hi>with the dogs of the heard; Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> hath lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g been kept <hi>on foot, cogitur ire pede,</hi> yet bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be our God, ſince the firſt <hi>howre</hi> of <hi>reformation</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this time,<note place="margin">Aboue <hi>40</hi> ſons of anciently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended knights ſtudents in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, &amp; moſt of them already miniſters now in Oxford.</note> never were ſo many &amp; ſo worthy ſonnes of the <hi>Prophets</hi> many worthily, ſome <hi>honourably</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs deſcended and conſecrated herevnto. <hi>Archippus</hi> looke to thy charge, watch, ſtand faſt <hi>in the faith,</hi> pray, exhort, rebuke, with al <hi>power,</hi> with al authority. Preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, let no man deſpiſe yee. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15625:22"/>nedum vita tua mala no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit per nequitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>videarur ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la per negligentiam, Sit veſtra cura no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nummorum ſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bern.</hi> ſeeke not ſo much <hi>the church goods</hi> as the <hi>churches good, leſt your right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forget her cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All of you, <hi>Ho. Rever. bleſſed,</hi> &amp; <hi>beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> all of you that are come hither, to this great <hi>Comitial</hi> aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that are come to this <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> to find <hi>Ieſus</hi> in the midſt of the <hi>Doctours,</hi> remember <hi>Ieruſalem, Religion</hi> and <hi>knowledge,</hi> the <hi>mother</hi> and the <hi>daughter, nobile par,</hi> the <hi>Naomi</hi> and the <hi>Ruth,</hi> the bleſſed <hi>paire</hi> of <hi>Cherubins</hi> over the Mercy ſeat, let them <hi>both</hi> haue your beſt <hi>wiſhes,</hi> and partake of your beſt <hi>workes,</hi> in that yee doe any thing to theſe, yee doe it to <hi>Chriſt.</hi> All <hi>poſterities,</hi> ſhall bleſſe the name of thoſe, our <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy preſent founders,</hi> whoſe <hi>workes</hi> be aſpiring, <hi>&amp; quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iam maenia ſurgunt.</hi> The <hi>bleſsing</hi> of <hi>Iuda,</hi> the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of <hi>Levi,</hi> the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of both <hi>teſtaments,</hi> of both lifes, ſhall be vpon <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>poſteritie</hi> forever. Their <hi>names</hi> ſhall be honoured, their <hi>examples</hi> imitated, and their <hi>workes</hi> ſhall praiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>the gates,</hi> and <hi>their right hand ſhall never forget her cunning.</hi> When wee ſhall all meet in the higher <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in that great aſſembly of all <hi>Saints,</hi> we <hi>ſhall ſee theſe rewarded,</hi> with <hi>Palmes</hi> in their <hi>hands,</hi> and <hi>Crownes</hi> on their <hi>heads,</hi> let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my <hi>beloued, covet</hi> theſe ſpiritual things, let vs do ſome ſervice to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> here, that <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> may crowne vs <hi>hence.</hi> Which that wee may <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> the <hi>Lord grant</hi> vs, all ſuch meaſure of his <hi>ſpirit</hi> of his <hi>grace,</hi> that abounding here in <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>good workes,</hi> we may <hi>receaue</hi> the reward promiſed, <hi>Come yee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15625:23"/>bleſſed of my father, receaue the kingdome provided from the beginning of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To God the Father, God the Sonne, God the holy Spirit, be all praiſe, all Power, all honour, this day, and all the daies of our life in this place and all Congregations of his Saints for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15625:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
